Collection of Confederate States of America Legal Tender MS187
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Collection of Confederate States of America Legal Tender
1861 -- 1865
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS187
0.75 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Custodial History
These materials were found in the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives in 2011; the Ryder collection was cataloged as part of the WPA in 1939/1940 but in later decades the catalog (A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of the Confederate Archives at Tufts College 1940) was forgotten and library staff added other materials to the Ryder collection, usually items from the South, from the 18th and 19th century and around the time of the Civil War. Because these materials were not part of the original Ryder collection, items were removed and a separate, 'artificial' collection was created.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains currency, loans, bonds, and a stamp by the Confederate States of America, and two Civil War currency notes from Virginia banks.
Biographical / Historical
The Confederate States of America was a collection of eleven Southern states which formed a government when they seceded from the Union in 1860-1861. The government was led by Jefferson Davis, and lasted until the spring of 1865. Though the Confederacy carried on a major war, it ultimately was never recognized as a sovereign nation, and was disbanded after its defeat in the Civil War.
Prior to the outbreak of the war, the South felt their economy and traditions threatened by rising abolitionist sentiment in the North. With the election of Abraham Lincoln, seven states initially seceded from the Union: Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, South Carolina, and Texas. After the first shots of the Civil War were fired at Fort Sumter, Arkansas, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia additionally joined the Confederacy. Headed by President Jefferson Davis, the Confederacy created its own constitution, modeled after the U.S. Constitution. They also issued their own stamps and currency and adopted their own flag.
The principal issue of the Confederacy was raising and equipping an army to fight Union forces. Though bolstered by initial victories in 1861 and 1862, the army was defeated in battles at Gettysburg and Vicksburg, which shattered the illusion of the supremacy of their army. General Robert E. Lee and General Joseph E. Johnston were able to fend off the Northern armies in the North and West for a time, but ultimately were worn down by dwindling manpower and stronger Union armies. After the surrender of Robert E. Lee on April 9th, 1865, Confederate generals in the South subsequently surrendered or disbanded their armies. The Confederacy ceased to exist with the end of the Civil War, and each state was readmitted to the Union in the Reconstruction Era, after individually ratifying the 13th Amendment to the Constitution.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Civil War; Money -- Confederate States of America; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
- Confederate bonds, loans, currency and stamp, 1861 -- 1865; MS187.001; 0.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Includes Confederate States bonds, loans, currency and stamp and two civil war currency notes from Virginia banks.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by classification system of published catalogs (all referenced).
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Cotton Certificate for a $1000 bond, 1862; MS187.001.001.00001 (Box Shared 5)
    1 item, two fragments. Cotton Certificate for a $1,000 bond. Not numbered, no issue. Cotton Certificate for a $1000 bond. Dated Richmond lst November,1862 for 20 bales of cotton of 10,000 lbs. weight, to be delivered on demand by the Government at the port of New Orleans or Mobile on receiving thirty days notice. The demand to be made within the six months after the declaration of peace, in default of a demand within that period, the Certificate may be discharged by payment of $1000 with interest at 6% from the date of issue.
  - 6 Percent Cotton Interest Bonds, 1863; MS187.001.001.00002 (Box Shared 5)
    Act of April 30, 1863
    4 items
    6% Cotton Interest Bonds
    Type 152 $1,000
    Illustrated with portrait of James A. Seddon of Va., CSA Secretary of War
    Printed on white paper
    Imprint Evans and; Cogswell, Columbia, S. C.
    No engraver listed
    Unissued. Not numbered, not signed.
    Left hand corner all 4 items have a faded squarish red stamp that bled through from the back page; stamp has rounded corners and in its center there is a red tree with an identical design left and right of tree (uncipherable)surrounded by 56a text: Department CSA Treasury. Towards left hand corner all 4 items have engraved [handwritten] Sullivan; there must have been 2 plates as there are two versions of the engraved signature in capital letters.
    Source: Ball, Douglas B., Comprehensive Catalog and History of Confederate Bonds (BNR Press, Port Clinton, Ohio 1998)
  - Ten cents Confederate Treasury Note, Bank of the Empire State, 1863; MS187.001.001.00003 (Box Shared 5)
    GA-250 Bank of the Empire State, ca 1857-1860, Rome Georgia
    Civil War Fractional Issues: Notes Payable in Confederate Treasury Notes (1863)
    G[enuine]42 10 cents, April 1, 1863 [date fully engraved], similar to 20 cents, G44
    No Imprint and engraver
    Bottom right corner woman leaning on a barrel and a tied up bale? In her left hand holding a scepter with two snakes
    will pay to bearer on demand ten cents in confederate treasury notes when presented in sums of five dollars. April 1st 1863.'
    Unsigned by Cashier
    Source: Haxby, J. A., Standard Catalog of United States Obsolete Bank Notes, 1782-1866 (Krause Publications)
  - 4 percent registered stock certificate, 1864; MS187.001.001.00004 (Box Shared 5)
    Act of February 17, 1864
    5 items.
    4% registered stock certificate, Section 2.
    No series.
    Includes transfer form on the back and stub on the left.
    Printed on white paper.
    Imprint: Eng.d by Geo. Dunn and Co. Richmond, Va.
    Unissued. Not signed. Not recorded. Not entered.
    Stubs on left bottom corner have oval stamp in red, reading: GOOD Treasury. In the middle initials probably reading RHE
  - Four percent certificate of indebtness, 1864; MS187.001.001.00005 (Box Shared 5)
    Authorization Feb 17, 1864
    No Amount, field left empty to be filled by hand, ditto number and signatures.
    Unused bond.
    4% certificate of indebtness, payable two years after peace. Passed under Act to reduce the Currency and to authorize a new issue of Notes and Bonds Feb 17 1864.
    Evans and Cogswell, Columbia S.C.
  - Eight percent coupon bonds, 1863; MS187.001.001.00006 (Box Shared 5)
    Authorization Act of February 20, 1863
    11 bonds.
    8% coupon bonds.
    Type 133 $500, Imprint: Evans and Cogswell, Columbia, S. C.
    Printed on tan paper, different from the rest of this bond issue. The loan medallion is octagonal because the corners are clipped off.
    Unissued. All 11 coupons ($20) attached.
  - Four percent coupon bonds, 1863; MS187.001.001.00007 (Box Shared 5)
    Authorization Act of March 23, 1863
    2 bonds
    4% coupon bonds
    Type 146 $1,000
    Engraved by George Dunn, printed by Hoyer and Ludwig
    Washington equestrian monument [used in confederate coat of arms] west of the Virginia Capitol in Richmond)
    Printed on tan paper.
    All 9 coupons($20) attached.
    Unissued.
    One item has fragment of red stamp on right bottom corner; bottom corner partially torn off. Second item also has right bottom corner removed (possibly also had red stamp there.). Folds and tear
  - Eight percent coupon bonds, 1862; MS187.001.001.00008 (Box Shared 5)
    Authorization Act of Dec. 10, 1862
    Eight percent coupon bonds due July 1st 1878
    Type 95 $500
    Illustrated with Judah P. Benjamin portrait
    Number issued: 2,016
    Signed by Robert Tyler, (1816-1877), second register of the treasury, son of US President John Tyler by his first wife.
    27 coupons still attached, numbered and signed by E. S. Read.
    Printed by B. Duncan, Columbia, S.C.
  - Eight percent coupon bonds, 1863; MS187.001.001.00009 (Box Shared 5)
    Authorization Act of February 20 1963
    1 bond
    Eight coupon bonds
    Illustrated with portrait of Vice President Alexander H. Stephens
    Type 132 $100, Imprint: Evans and Cogswell, Columbia, S. C.
    Date of Issue: March 2 1863. Number issued: 28,760 [higher than indicated numbers in reference source]
    Lower right-hand corner: G(eorge) Wojciechovoski [sic], Lith.
    Not signed by register of the treasury.
    Entered and recorded
    All 11 coupons ($4) attached; last coupon is missing all currency imprints. ($4) Coupons all signed by B. B. Jones
  - Seven percent coupon bond, 1863; MS187.001.001.00010 (Box Shared 5)
    4 bond
    Seven percent coupon bond
    Illustrated with Confederate officer overlooking the Rappahannock River west of Fredericksburg; bottom small illustration shows a steam boat against the backdrop of town (Richmond?)
    Type 136 Denomination $100
    Imprint Archer and Daly, Richmond, Va.
    Printed on pink paper.
    Date of Issue: March 2 1863
    Unsigned. All 10 coupons (for 6 month interest) attached.
  - Hundred dollar bills, 1861; MS187.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    Authorization: March 9th 1861
    Denomination $100
    40 notes.
    Type 5. This is one of six note types actually signed by the register and treasurer. The government issues from Richmond were signed by the new register of the treasury, Robert Tyler, the son of U. S. President Tyler. Issued by Southern Bank Company, New Orleans.
    No Series
    Catalog number 6
    Serial letter B
    Signed Aug. 28, 1861. Serial numbers: 345-352, 354-357, 382, 719-722, 724-725, 749-755, 760, 1537, 1656-1659. Signed Sept. 6, 1861. Serial numbers: 2808-2815, 2817-2818, 3080-3083, 3088-3090, 3092, 3097-3100, 3731-3732. Signed Sept. 10, 1861. Serial numbers: 3929. Signed Sept. 11, 1861. Serial numbers: 4242-4245. Signed Sept. 12, 1861. Serial numbers: 4788-4798.
    Signed by treasurer: Edward C. Elmore
    Signed by register: Robert Tyler
    Illustrations: Hudson River Railroad scene at center. Justice left and Minerva right. Black with green overprint red-fiber paper. Bears interest One Cent Per Day. Some endorsed on back Received, Savannah, April 21 1863. Principal fo [sic] within Note, and Four hundred and Twenty Five Days Interest. And then dated and signed. All notes cancelled: cut cancel [slits of some design or shape, usually a cross with a bank hammer]; cut out cancel [some paper usually round or triangular shape removed; punch out cancel [small round holes].
    Source: Criswell, Grover C. with Douglas B. Ball and Hugh Shull, Comprehensive Catalog of Confederate Paper Money (BNR Press: Ohio 1996)
    Imprint: Southern Bank Note Company, New Orleans, although printed by the American Bank Note Company branch office in New Orleans.
  - Hundred dollar bills, 1861; MS187.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Fifty dollar bills, 1861; MS187.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
    Denomination $50
    35 notes.
    Type 6. This is the last of the six note types actually signed by the register and treasurer. The government issues from Richmond were signed by the new register of the treasury, Robert Tyler, the son of U. S. President Tyler. This is the first Confederate note to bear a portrait of George Washington. Who as the father of the country, was claimed by both North and South. Issued by Southern Bank Company, New Orleans.
    Signed April 28, 1861. Serial numbers: 138, 141-143, 146, 147, 149, 150, 157-162. Signed August 18, 1861. Serial numbers: 1072, 1077, 1627-1629, 1634, 1634-1636, 1638-1642. Signed Sept. 6, 1861. Serial numbers: 2803-2804, 2806-2808. Signed Sept. 12, 1861. Serial numbers: 4864, 5603.
    Illustrations: Justice left, Agriculture and Industry seated on bale of cotton. Washington, right. Black with green overprint, red-fiber paper. Bears interest Half a Cent Per Day. Some endorsed on back Received, Savannah, April 21 1863. Principal fo [sic] within Note, and Four hundred and Twenty Five Days Interest. And then dated and signed. All notes cancelled: cut cancel [slits of some design or shape, usually a cross with a bank hammer]; cut out cancel [some paper usually round or triangular shape removed; punch out cancel [small round holes].
  - Twenty dollar bill, 1861; MS187.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
    Authorization: September 12, 1861
    Denomination $20
    3rd Issue
    Type 18
    Fragment, most information not determinable
    Series
    Catalog number
    Serial letter
    Serial number: 18881 [?]
    Signed for register:
    Signed for treasurer:
    Illustrations: Large sailing vessel. Sailor at capstan, left. Blank back.
    Engraver: Hoyer and Ludwig, Richmond VA
  - Two dollar bill, 1862; MS187.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
    Authorization: April 18th 1862
    Denomination $2
    4th Issue
    Type 42
    Dated June 2, 1862
    Worn and fragment, some information not determinable
    3 Series
    Catalog number 337
    Serial number 9
    Serial number: 7 [?] 4 050
    Illustrations: Personification of the South striking down Union, J. P. Benjamin left. Back blank. Without the green 2 and TWO overprint
    Engraver: B. Duncan, Columbia, S. C.
  - One dollar bill, 1862; MS187.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
    Denomination $1
    Type 44
    Dated June 2 1862
    Worn and fragment, most information not determinable
    Series illegible
    Catalog number 339 (probably)
    Serial number: 10
    Illustrations: Steamship at sea. Lucy Holcombe Pickens (wife of the Governor of S. C.) right. Liberty at left. Back blank. No green overprint.
  - One dollar bill, 1862; MS187.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
    Worn
    Series 1
    Catalog number: 339
    Serial number: 9
  - One dollar bill, 1862; MS187.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
    Catalog number 339
  - One dollar bill, 1862; MS187.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
    Worn and fragment
  - Fifty cent bill, 1863; MS187.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
    Authorization: April 6th 1863
    Denomination 50 cents
    6th Issue
    Type 63
    worn and fragment
    1st Series
    Catalog number 485
    Serial letter A
    Serial number 6754 (printed in red)
    Signed for register: facsimile signature Robert Tyler
    Signed for treasurer: facsimile signature E. C. Elmore
    Illustrations: Bust of President Jefferson Davis. Supposed to be printed on pink paper: faded to beige. Back blank.
    Engraver: Archer and Daly, Richmond, Va.
  - Fifty cent bill, 1863; MS187.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
    worn
    Catalog number (not listed as a different printer/engraver; otherwise number 485)
    Serial letter C
    Serial number 78647 (printed in red)
    Illustrations: Bust of President Jefferson Davis. Supposed to be printed on pink paper. Back blank.
    Engraver: Archer and Halpin, Richmond, Va.
  - Fifty cent bill, 1863; MS187.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
    2nd Series
    Catalog number 488
    Serial number 45034 (printed in red)
  - One hundred dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
    Authorization: February 17, 1864
    Type 65
    Catalog number 490
    Serial number 92862
    Signed for register: Laval, Miss S. E.
    Signed for treasurer: Miller, Miss Alice M.
    Illustrations: Lucy H. Pickens, wife of the Governor of S. C. in center, two soldiers left. George W. Randolph right. Black is blue with large HUNDRED and four circular medallions with 100 at the corners.
    Engraver: Keating and Ball, Columbia, S. C.
  - One hundred dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - One hundred dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
    Catalog number 493b
    Serial number 92199
    Signed for register: Proctor, Mrs. E. S.
    Signed for treasurer: Macmurdo, Miss Rosa
  - Twenty dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
    Type 67
    Series 4 (4 appears to be written in by hand)
    Catalog number 508 (two flourishes over ica of America)
    Serial number 27506
    Signed for register: Cullen, Miss M. E.
    Signed for treasurer: illegible
    Illustrations: State capitol of Nashville, Tennessee, A. H. Stephens at right. Black with redissh network background overprint. Ornate blue back with twenty in large letters.
  - Twenty dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00017 (Box 2)
    XI Series
    Catalog number 515 (two flourishes over ica of America)
    Serial number 24775
    Signed for register: illegible
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00018 (Box 2)
    Denomination $10
    Issue 7
    Type 68
    no series
    Catalog number 540
    Serial letter: A
    Serial number: 15586
    Signed for register: Gilliam, Mrs. M. A.
    Signed for treasurer: Dennison, Miss E. A.
    Illustrations: Hoses pulling cannon, R. M. T. Hunter at right; black with reddish overprint
    Engraver: Keatinge and Ball, Columbia, S. C.
    Printer: Evans and Cogswell
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00019 (Box 2)
    Serial letter: B
    Signed for register: Dabney, Miss Bettie
    Signed for treasurer: Haynes, Miss Rich
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00020 (Box 2)
    Serial letter: F
    Serial number: 90633
    Signed for register: Bailey, Miss M. W.
    Signed for treasurer: Clarke, Miss Bettie J.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00021 (Box 2)
    Serial letter: G
    Serial number: 16393
    Signed for register: Taylor, Mrs. Miriam
    Signed for treasurer: Irvine, Mrs. M. C.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00022 (Box 2)
    Denomination: $10
    Catalog number 542
    Serial number: 47108
    Signed for register: Rhett, Mrs. F. M.
    Signed for treasurer: Logan, Miss J.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00023 (Box 2)
    Catalog number 545
    Serial number: B-983
    Signed for register: Bernard, Miss Fannie. E.
    Signed for treasurer: Reed, Miss Emma S.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00024 (Box 2)
    Serial letter: C
    Serial number: 18552
    Signed for register: Hayes, S. C.
    Signed for treasurer: Reeves, Miss M. C.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00025 (Box 2)
    Serial number: 88928
    Signed for register: Courtney, Mrs. L.
    Signed for treasurer: Morris, Miss C. S.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00026 (Box 2)
    4 Series
    Catalog number 546
    Serial letter: D
    Serial number: 17896
    Signed for treasurer: Gott, Miss Julia F.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00027 (Box 2)
    Series 3
    Serial letter H
    Serial number 13010
    Signed for register: Gilloiam, Miss M. E.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00028 (Box 2)
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00029 (Box 2)
    5 Series
    Catalog number 547
    Serial number: 7372
    Signed for register: Norris, Mrs. L. A.
    Signed for treasurer: Scott, Miss S.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00030 (Box 2)
    Serial number: 53665
    Signed for register: Alexander, H. E.
    Signed for treasurer: Armstrong, [first initial illegible but not L.]
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00031 (Box 2)
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00032 (Box 2)
    6 Series
    Catalog number 548
    Serial letter: E
    Serial number: 5235
    Signed for treasurer: Sauxay, Miss Sophia G.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00033 (Box 2)
    Serial number: 63654
    Signed for register: Morton, Miss M. C.
    Signed for treasurer: Semple, Miss Nannie
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00034 (Box 2)
    8 Series
    Catalog number 550
    Serial number: 25435
    Signed for treasurer: Snead, W. T.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00035 (Box 2)
    Serial number: 46791
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00036 (Box 2)
    9 Series
    Catalog number 551
    Serial number: 52572
    Signed for register: King, Miss R. B.
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00037 (Box 2)
    Denomination $5
    Type 69
    Catalog number 558
    Serial number 89933
    Signed for register: Wingate Miss E.C.
    Signed for treasurer: Sims Miss L.
    Illustrations: State capitol of Richmond, Va, center; C. G. Memminger, right. Reddish network overprint background. Ornate blue back with Five in large letters.
    Lithograph: Evans and Cogswell
  - Ten dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00038 (Box 2)
    Serial letter D
    Serial number 16456
    Signed for register: Southall, Miss Sallie
  - Five dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00039 (Box 2)
    fragment
    Series 4
    Catalog number 561
    Serial letter G
    Serial number 47073
    Signed for register: Thayer, C. C,
    Signed for treasurer: Angel, Mrs. J. H.
  - Five dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00040 (Box 2)
    Serial number 27851
    Signed for register: Holmes, Mrs. L. L.
    Signed for treasurer: Wingate, Mrs. N. E.
  - Five dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00041 (Box 2)
    Serial number 90839
  - Five dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00042 (Box 2)
    Series 5
    Catalog number 562
    Serial letter F
    Serial number 44014
    Signed for register: Pelot, Mrs. A. P.
  - Five dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00043 (Box 2)
    Series 6
    Catalog number 563
    Serial number 93989
  - Five dollar bill, 1864; MS187.001.002.00044 (Box 2)
    Series 7
    Catalog number 564
    Serial number 2574
    Signed for treasurer: Korff, Miss Kate
    Lithograph: Evans Cogswell
  - Five dollar bill, Trans-Alleghany Bank of Virginia, Jeffersonville, 1865; MS187.001.002.00045 (Box 2)
    Trans-Alleghany Bank of Virginia, Jeffersonville: 1853-ca.1855, but bank notes were dated and used up to the 1860s.
    Hand written date: March 10th 1865
    Catalog number 110-G2
    Serial number 1786
    Signed by state treasurer: Thomas Mons[sp?]
    Signed by cashier and president of bank
    Engraver: Danforth, Wright and Co, New York and Philad.
    Source: Haxby, J. A., Standard Catalog of United States Obsolete Bank Notes, 1782-1866 (Krause Publications: DVD 2009)
  - One dollar bill, Virginia Treasury Note, Richmond, 1862; MS187.001.002.00046 (Box 2)
    Printed date: May 15 1862
    Serial number 49153
    Signed for treasurer: J. S. Calvert
    Signed for Aud. Pub. Acct.
    Illustration: Maiden with pail seated on log at the center. Large red ONE protector below. Oval portrait of Governor Letcher at the lower left.
    Engraver: Hoyer and Ludwig, Richmond.
  - 5 cent Jefferson Davis stamp, 1861; MS187.001.002.00047 (Box 2)
    This is either the first or second issue of the first stamp issued by the Confederate States since the faded stamps make it impossible to determine if stamps are blueish or greenish and the color indicates the issue. The stamp is the first stamp issued on American soil to display the likeness of a living president and is also the first stamp printed by stone lithography.
    Designer and Engraver: Charles Ludwig. Printing Method: Stone Lithography. Lithographer: Hoyer and Ludwig, Richmond, Virginia.